Guide to the Joyce Matz Papers 1969-2017 MS 3050
New-York Historical Society
Joyce Matz papers
1969-2017
New-York Historical Society
Matz, Joyce, 1925-2017
MS 3050
22 Linear feet (in 22 record cartons)
Papers of public relations consultant and historic preservationist Joyce Matz (1925–2017), who represented such varied clients as Congressman Mario Biaggi, the Eastern Paralyzed Veterans Association, and the Armenian Church of America. In her role of chair or co-chair of the Landmarks Committee of Manhattan Community Board 5, she fought to protect iconic New York City structures like Lever House, Town Hall, and St. Bartholomew's Church from alteration or demolition. She often provided pro bono publicity for the various coalitions, committees, and friends groups that lobbied to oppose outsized developments like Donald Trump's "Television City" complex proposed for the 60th Street Rail Yard. Includes press releases, publicity materials, newspaper clippings, notes, research, some correspondence, photographs, and a small amount of audiovisual material (restricted).
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Note that the New-York Historical Society lacks playback equipment for the audiovisual material in box 22.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Suzanne Matz, Linda Matz, and John Matz, children of Joyce Matz, September 2017.
Arrangement
The Joyce Matz Papers are organized in three series devised by the archivist:
Series I.
Historic Preservation and quality of life issues, 1978-2013.
Series II.
Public Relations, 1969-2009.
Series III.
General files, photographs, and audiovisual material, 1971-2017.
File names within Series I and II are derived or expanded from Matz's own (see the container list). The sheer number of newspaper clippings saved by Matz to document her work prohibited the archivist from arranging material in strictly chronological order. The researcher should, therefore, consult every folder listed under the same topic to catch items that may be out of place.
Biographical/Historical Note
"The Woman Who Likes Buildings" is the succinct title one newspaper bestowed on Joyce Matz (1925–2017), whose four-decade career in historic preservation led her everywhere at once in Manhattan. Her strong voice could be heard in virtually every fight to save a threatened landmark; her public relations expertise lent validity to the cause of every coalition formed to protect a neighborhood from outsized development.
A child of the city, Matz was born in Manhattan on 20 May 1925 to Harold and Elsie (Corday) Arnstam. She grew up on West 77th Street, next door to the New-York Historical Society, which she passed each day on her way to and from the Ethical Culture School on Central Park West. Matz graduated from Ethical Culture's Fieldston School in 1943. She took a bachelor's degree in English from Mount Holyoke College and would later do graduate work at Smith College and Columbia University. In 1947 she married Mortimer Matz, with whom she would have three children: John, Linda, and Suzanne.
With her husband, a lawyer and one-time reporter for the Daily News, Joyce Matz began her career as a public relations consultant. Starting around 1960, she worked with him as vice president and partner of Mortimer Matz Associates (later called Matz & Matz Associates). Then, after her 1979 divorce and until her death in 2017, she worked for herself as Joyce Matz Associates. She provided publicity to metropolitan, national, and foreign newspapers, as well as radio and television, for a varied client list that included individuals (like John Zervas, "Hot Dog King of Central Park"), politicians (Congressman Mario Biaggi), businesses (Gallery Passport, an art tour service), religious organizations (Armenian Church of America), and charitable groups (Eastern Paralyzed Veterans Association). For fuller descriptions, see the Series II container list.
Matz credited a story in National Geographic about the sinking of Venice (which she had never seen) with awakening the sense of panicked urgency she applied to saving the historic fabric of New York. Its buildings were not sinking, but nevertheless they were under attack from greedy property owners and developers with plans inappropriate to the neighborhoods they would affect. In 1977 Manhattan Borough President Percy Sutton appointed Matz to Community Board 5 (bounded roughly by 59th Street, Lexington Avenue, 14th Street, Sixth Avenue, 26th Street, and Eighth Avenue). She would chair or co-chair the CB5's Landmarks Committee for 15 years, overseeing iconic structures and neighborhoods in the heart of Midtown Manhattan, such as the Flatiron Building and the Ladies' Mile Historic District. Any application to demolish or alter a landmarked structure, or any proposal for a new designation, came to Matz's committee for rejection or approval. Occasionally she would recuse herself from voting because she was also providing publicity (sometimes pro bono) for the committees, coalitions, and friends groups that lobbied for or against the proposals.
The myriad campaigns in which Matz played a role is long and best grasped by perusing the container list for Series I, but some of her successful fights include preserving St. Bartholomew's Church (which hoped to sell its community house site for an office tower), the Beacon Theatre (which would have been irreparably damaged by its conversion to a discotheque), Town Hall (landmarked in large part by Matz's efforts), and the City & Suburban Homes Company's Avenue A Estate (a complex of model tenements developer Peter Kalikow sought to demolish). She lost many battles, too, most poignantly, perhaps, the one to save the Cottages and Garden, a 1937 enclave of eight apartments that opened onto a private green space behind a Third Avenue commercial building; the complex failed to win landmark designation and was replaced by a condominium tower (see boxes 13–15).
In 2000 Joyce Matz received the Elliot Willensky Fund award for her campaign to secure landmark designation for a group of townhouses on East 54th and East 55th Streets (see box 7, folders 7–12). The following year she was named the Historic Districts Council's 2000 Landmarks Lion in recognition of her unusual devotion to historic districts and landmarks (see box 9, folders 4–6). Shortly before her death she was still at it, touring with a reporter the closed Roman Catholic Church of Our Lady Queen of Angels, which she fought to landmark (as yet undesignated). Joyce Matz died at home in Manhattan on 18 September 2017, aged 92.
[This note is based on various iterations of Joyce Matz's resume (see box 22, folder 7), two newspaper profiles--(1) Al Amateau, "The Woman Who Likes Buildings" from The Westsider (January 16-22, 1986) and (2) Edward-Isaac Dovere, "A Champion for Preservation" from Our Town (November 18, 2004)--as well as her New York Times obituary by Sam Roberts, "Joyce Matz, Fervid Voice for Historic Preservation, Dies at 92" (September 19, 2017). In 2007 Keenan Hughes, a graduate student at Pratt Institute, interviewed Matz for the New York Preservation Archive Project's Oral History Collection; their recorded conversation and a transcript are available at www.nypap.org/oral-history/joyce-matz/.]
Scope and Contents
Virtually every file in the Joyce Matz Papers contains notes, research, press releases, and tear sheets stemming from her historic preservation activism or public relations work. Some include correspondence, ephemera, and photographs. The voluminous newspaper and magazine clippings Matz saved document the countless stories she fed to the press. Descriptions of her public relations campaigns and preservation issues appear at the folder level in the container list.
The researcher should be aware that Matz was in the habit of taking notes or printing out drafts of releases on stationery recycled from unrelated projects; see, for instance, the file for Friends of Hudson River Park (box 8, folder 2), which includes letterhead from the Brooklyn Historic Railway Association (see box 1, folder 5), and S.O.U.L. (Save Our Universalist Landmark; box 15, folder 3).
Carnegie Hill Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Central Park (New York, N.Y.); Ellis Island (N.J. and N.Y.); Hudson River Waterfront Park (New York, N.Y.); Madison Square North Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Midtown Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Tudor City (New York, N.Y.); Upper East Side (New York, N.Y.); Upper East Side Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Upper West Side (New York, N.Y.); Upper West Side/Central Park West Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Historic buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic districts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historic preservation.; Tenants' associations; Tetrachloroethylene; Theaters -- New York (State) -- New York.; Letters (correspondence).; Notes (documents).; Press clippings.; Press kits.; Press releases.; Promotional materials.; Public relations; Publicity; Tear sheets.; Biaggi, Mario; Julien, Alfred S., 1910-; Krim, Arthur B., 1910-1994; Lloyd, Anamaria; Matz, Joyce, 1925-2017; Pollack, William (Attorney); Sills, Richard Reynolds; Velella, Guy J., 1944-2011; Zeferetti, Leo C., 1927-2018; Zervas, John (Hot dog vendor); 92nd Street Y (New York, N.Y.); Acrison, Inc; African Burial Ground (New York, N.Y.); Armenian Church. Diocese of the Armenian Church of America; Brooklyn Educational & Cultural Alliance; Brooklyn Historic Railway Association; Bryant Park Restoration Corporation; Carnegie Hill Neighbors; Cathedral of St. John the Divine (New York, N.Y.); Catholic Interracial Council of New York; Central Park West Preservation Committee; CitiNeighbors Coalition of Historic Carnegie Hill; Coalition for a Livable West Side (New York, N.Y.); Coalition to Save City & Suburban Housing (New York, N.Y.); Coalition to Save the Lincoln Square Home for Adults; Coalition to Save the Naumburg Bandshell; Committee for Fair Options on Walden School Construction; Committee for New York; Committee to Oppose the Sale of St. Bartholomew's Church; Community Board 5 (Manhattan, New York, N.Y.); Concerned Tenants of 823 Park Avenue; Correction Captains' Association (New York, N.Y.); Defenders of the Historic Upper East Side; East 79th Street Block Association (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Paralyzed Veterans Association (U.S.); Friends of Hudson River Park; Friends of the High School for Environmental Studies; Friends of the Upper East Side Historic Districts; Gallery Passport, Ltd. (New York, N.Y.); Government and Community Together for Legal Lives (New York, N.Y.); Grand Central Partnership; Gregory Towers Tenants' Coordinating Committee; Guggenheim Neighbors; Historic Districts Council (New York, N.Y.); J.M. Kaplan Fund; Lambs (New York, N.Y.); Landmark West! (Group: New York, N.Y.); Lever House (New York, N.Y.); Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center; Metropolitan Club (New York, N.Y.); Mount Holyoke Club of New York; Moynihan Station (New York, N.Y.); Municipal Art Society of New York; Nathan's Famous; National Coalition For Family Justice; Neighbors R Us (New York, N.Y.); New York Committee for a Balanced Building Boom; New York Landmarks Conservancy; New York (State). Office of Parks and Recreation; People for the American Way; People for Westpride (New York, N.Y.); Plaza Hotel (New York, N.Y.); Preserve the Landmarks and Character of the East Eighties (New York, N.Y.); St. Bartholomew's Episcopal Church (New York, N.Y.); Save Our Universalist Landmark (New York, N.Y.); Save the Beacon Theatre Committee; Save the Coogan Coalition (New York, N.Y.); Save the Cottages and Garden (New York, N.Y.); Save the Whales (Organization); Seventh Regiment Armory (New York, N.Y.); Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum; Student Athletes, Inc.; Superior Officers Association of the New York City Housing Authority Police Department; Sutton Area Community; Tavern on the Green; Town Hall, Inc.; Tudor City Association; Washington Square Outdoor Art Exhibit; Women's City Club of New York; York Avenue Estate (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I. Historic Preservation and quality of life issues, 1971-2013; 17 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  Press releases, news clippings, tear sheets, correspondence, and notes for the myriad historic preservation campaigns and quality of life issues on which Joyce Matz consulted and supported. See descriptions at the folder level. A number of these files, although not originally designated as such by Matz, stem from her time as chair or co-chair of the Landmarks Committee of Manhattan Community Board 5. Researchers should, therefore, explore the 17 files of Community Board 5 material (box 5, folders 5-13, and box 6, folders 1-8) for potential additional coverage of an issue outside its designated folder(s).
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized alphabetically by the name of the specific project (e.g., building or street address) or preservation group (e.g., coalition, committee) for which Joyce Matz provided publicity and support. The sheer number of newspaper clippings saved by Matz to document her work prohibited the archivist from arranging material in strictly chronological order. The researcher should, therefore, consult every folder listed under the same topic to catch items that may be out of place.
  - Abigail Adams Smith Museum & Glick Project, 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Opposition to developer Jeffrey Glick's plan to construct a twin-towered complex directly across the street from the landmarked 1799 Abigail Adams Smith House (now called the Mount Vernon Hotel Museum, 421 East 61st Street).
  - African Burial Ground, 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Newspaper clippings regarding the fate of the African Burial Ground, which would gain landmark designation in 1993 as part of the African Burial Ground & the Commons Historic District.
  - Avenue of the Americas | West 28th and West 29th Streets, 1984-1987 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Development concerns for Avenue of the Americas (a.k.a. Sixth Avenue) between West 16th and West 23rd Streets, and for West 28th and West 29th Streets between Fifth Avenue and Broadway.
  - Brooklyn Educational & Cultural Alliance (B.E.C.A.), 1978-1979 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Press releases, newspaper clippings, and some correspondence regarding the B.E.C.A.'s activities, and a $33,000 grant it received from the State Board of Regents to provide educational and occupational training for battered women.
  - Brooklyn Historic Railway Association, 1982-2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    Press releases, newspaper clippings, and notes regarding the Brooklyn Historic Railway Association, which led tours of the 1844 Atlantic Avenue Tunnel (the world's oldest subway tunnel), and hoped to return historic streetcars to the borough.
  - Bryant Park Restoration Corporation [4 folders], 1982-1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6-9)
    Press releases, newspaper clippings, notes, and some correspondence documenting the activities of the Bryant Park Restoration Corporation, which in 1988 closed the crime-ridden park for a four-year renovation.
  - Carnegie Hill Neighbors, Inc. | 92nd Street Y, 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    Opposition to proposals by the 92nd Street Y to erect a building at 125 East 92nd Street.
  - Carnegie Hill Neighbors, Inc. | Smithers Mansion, 2000-2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    Opposition to plans by the Spence School to alter its building, the landmarked 1932 Smithers Mansion at 56 East 93rd Street.
  - Central Park South, 1997-2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Efforts to seek landmark protection for the length of Central Park South (i.e., West 59th Street between Fifth and Eighth Avenues), and specific buildings fronting it, such as 2 Columbus Circle and 240 Central Park South (the latter was designated in 2002).
  - Central Park West Preservation Committee, Inc., 1983-1984 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    Efforts to stop the New-York Historical Society's proposed residential tower above its building at 170 Central Park West. For a later, similar plan, see box 15, folder 10.
  - Citi Neighbors Coalition of Historic Carnegie Hill [4 folders], 1999-2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14-17)
    Opposition to Citibank's plan to sell the air rights above its branch office at Madison Avenue and East 91st Street. Zoning permitted a potential twelve-story building on the site, but the Citi Neighbors Coalition sought to have Citibank require any new construction to conform to the low-rise character of the neighborhood.
  - Coalition Against Lincoln West, Inc. [folders 1-4 of 8], 1983-1985 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18-21)
    In 1979 the Macri Group, an Argentine company, in partnership with investor Abe Hirschfeld, bought the 60th Street Rail Yard, and in they 1982 planned a 7,300,000-square-foot residential redevelopment for the site to be called Lincoln West. They were unable to obtain financing, so in 1985, Donald Trump bought the development rights for his proposed Television City. (For opposition to the latter, see the folders on the group Westpride in boxes 15-17).
  - Coalition Against Lincoln West, Inc. [folders 5-8 of 8], 1983-1985 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Coalition for a Livable West Side [6 folders], 1992-1997 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5-10)
    The Coalition for a Livable West Side, formed in 1981, a volunteer, environmental organization, draws its membership from individuals, tenant and block associations, and cooperative and condominium boards. In the early- to mid-1990s, the Coalition sought to block construction of Donald Trump's Riverside South, a 57-acre urban development project in the Lincoln Square neighborhood of Manhattan. Originated by Trump in partnership with six civic associations (Municipal Art Society, Natural Resources Defense Council, Parks Council, Regional Plan Association, Riverside Park Fund, and Westpride), the project replaced Trump's proposed Television City on the site of the failed Lincoln West residential development. (For Lincoln West, see Matz's files on the Coalition Against Lincoln West, in boxes 1-2; for Television City, see the files on Westpride in boxes 15-17.)
  - Coalition to Save City & Suburban Housing, Inc. [folders 1-2 of 15], 1985-2006 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11-12)
    In 1984 developer Peter S. Kalikow (who later owned the New York Post) bought the City and Suburban Homes Company's Avenue A (York Avenue) Estate, a complex of early twentieth-century model tenements for working-class families. Kalikow's plan to construct high-rise towers on the site (on the block bounded by East 78th Street, East 79th Street, York Avenue, and the FDR Drive) would have displaced thousands of residents, and, so, met fierce opposition. The complex received landmark protection in 1990; however, a portion was later stripped of that designation by the Board of Estimate at the request of Kalikow. In 1993 the courts overturned that decision and restored landmark status to the entire site.
  - Coalition to Save City & Suburban Housing, Inc. [folders 3-14 of 15], 1985-2006 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-12)
  - Coalition to Save City & Suburban Housing, Inc. [folder 15 of 15], 1985-2006 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - Coalition to Save the Lincoln Square Home for Adults, 1984 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    The builder of an apartment tower at West 68th Street and Broadway agreed to pay New York City $10 for every foot of bonus space allowed by the City Planning Commission. The resulting $280,530 was coveted by the residents of the Lincoln Square Home for Adults, who were facing eviction and hoped to use the money toward the purchase of their building (201 West 74th Street) before it was sold to a developer and replaced by conventional housing.
  - Coalition to Save the Naumburg Bandshell [2 folders], 1992-1993, 1999 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3-4)
    In 1989 the Central Park Conservancy and the Parks Department, in conjunction with restoration of The Mall, announced plans to demolish the Naumburg Bandshell. Nothing happened until 1992, when revived plans to tear down the bandshell, or move it to Riverside Park, or even to Peekskill, New York, raised the cries of preservationists. They were led by Christopher W. London, great-grandson of Elkan Naumburg, donor of the bandshell in 1923. The courts sided with the preservationists, blocking the bandshell's removal.
  - Committee for Fair Options on Walden School Construction, 1985 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    Efforts to block construction of a condominium tower above the Walden School at 1 West 88th Street, northwest corner of Central Park West.
  - Committee for New York, 1990 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
    Press releases, clippings, and materials for "Building the City We Need," a conference sponsored by the Committee for New York, 26 January 1990.
  - Committee to Oppose the Sale of St. Bartholomew's Church, Inc. [folders 1-11 of 12], 1984-1991 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7-17)
    In the 1980s part of the congregation of the landmarked St. Bartholomew's Church (325 Park Avenue) hoped to increase funding by replacing their community house (109 East 50th Street) with a 47-story office tower. The New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission twice rejected their application, and the case, which lasted until 1991, eventually went to the Supreme Court, which upheld the landmark designation but raised the question of whether religious structures should be exempt from historic, municipal ordinances.
  - Committee to Oppose the Sale of St. Bartholomew's Church, Inc. [folder 12 of 12], 1984-1991 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Committee to Save the Theatres [2 folders], 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2-3)
    Spurred by the recent demolition of the Helen Hayes and Morosco Theatres, the Committee to Save the Theatres sought landmark protection for 45 historic Broadway performance venues. Actress Colleen Dewhurst was among the famous names who lent support to the cause.
  - Committee to Stop the 42nd Street Light Rail, 1994-1996 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    Documentation of opposition to New York City's plan to install a trolley line along the length of 42nd Street, from the United Nations Plaza on the east, to a terminus at Twelfth Avenue between West 36th and 38th Streets on the west.
  - Community Board 5 Landmarks Committee [folders 1-9 of 17], circa 1977-2013 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5-13)
    Manhattan Community Board 5 is bounded (roughly) by 59th Street, Lexington Avenue, 14th Street, Sixth Avenue, 26th Street, and Eighth Avenue. In her long tenure as chair or co-chair of the board's Landmarks Committee, Joyce Matz had oversight of many iconic structures and enclaves in CB5's jurisdiction, such as the Flatiron Building and the Ladies' Mile Historic District. Any application to demolish or alter a landmarked structure, or any proposal for a new designation, came to her committee for rejection or approval. (For the landmarks within CB5's boundaries, refer to the Landmarks Preservation Commission's official map, which provides designation dates and links to designation reports.)
  - Community Board 5 Landmarks Committee [folders 10-17 of 17], circa 1977-2013 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-8)
  - Community Coalition | East 76th Street Rezoning [2 folders], 1999-2000 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9-10)
    In 1999 the developer of a large site at 506 East 76th Street applied to have the property rezoned from manufacturing to residential, hoping to capitalize on its maximum 31-story building potential. The City Planning Commission reduced the allowable height to 13 stories, which the community argued still exceeded an 8-story limit set in 1985 for all midblock areas of the Upper East Side.